אוקיי, בוקר טוב. Okay, boker tov. All right, so today's דף daf
is דף ח', daf chet, and we pick up with אמר מר
amar mar about eight lines from the top or seven lines from
the top, one two three, seven lines from the top, and we're
dealing with this issue that sometimes a כהן kohen will refuse to
look at a person's נגע, nega, a person's spot that might be
צרעת, tzara'at, because it is the wedding, a person's week of the
wedding, or it's the רגל, regel, and there's even a possibility even
for a דבר רשות, devar reshut, even for something that's not a
מצוה, mitzvah, it could be deferred to a more convenient time. אמר
מר. Amar mar. So let's take a look.
Does אמר מר amar mar always indicate necessarily a tannaic statement or
not necessarily? אמר מר, Amar mar, yeah, I
don't know, maybe there's an exception, I don't know, but אמר מר
amar mar goes back and looks at a ברייתא braita that was
quoted before.
Generally, it's signaling us generally,
it's
a requote of an earlier ברייתא, braita, yes.
And the difference between אמר מר amar mar and גופא gufa is
that אמר מר amar mar basically looks back at a line that
was quoted to further analyze the law, and גופא gufa goes back
when a line was quoted and puts it in the context of
the entire text. So if like an extract, an excerpt was quoted
earlier, גופא gufa will then look at the entire body of the
original source, whereas אמר מר, amar mar, you know, takes the line
that the excerpt that was quoted and goes deeper into it. So
that's the difference, but they're both looking back at a tannaic text
that was quoted, a ברייתא braita that was quoted earlier. So אמר
מר, amar mar, יש יום שאתה רואה בו ויש יום שאי אתה
רואה בו. yesh yom she'ata roeh bo ve'yesh yom she'ei ata roeh
bo. There's a day that you see and days that you will
refuse to see, and they learn it from וביום הראות בו. uveyom
hera'ot bo. So the גמרא Gemara says: מאי משמע, mai mashma, where
do you get that from the verse? The verse just says on
the day you see it, you will declare it טמא. tamei. Where
do you see that you can select or there's some selection of
which days you'll see it? So אמר אביי, amar Abaye, אם כן
לכתוב רחמנא ביום, im ken lichtov rachmana beyom, on the day that
you see it. מאי וביום, Mai uveyom, and on the day that
you see it? שמע מינה יש יום שאתה רואה בו ויש יום
שאי אתה רואה בו. shema mina yesh yom she'ata roeh bo ve'yesh
yom she'ei ata roeh bo. You see that there's some selection being
done of whether you're going to see it or not. So maybe
just the extra ו', vav, maybe some add the extra ו' vav
suggests like a moment of pause, you know, and on the day
that you see it, which means like there's some, you know, there's
some like decision that you're going to see it on that day.
That sort of pause that comes through the and. Anyway, somehow the
extra ו' vav tells אביי Abaye that there are days that you'll
see it and days you won't see it. רבא אמר, Rava amar,
כולא קרא יתירא הוא. kula kra yeteirah hu. No, no, no. The
whole verse, no, the word ביום beyom is extra, not just the
ו'. vav. דאם כן לכתוב רחמנא ובהראות בו, de'im ken lichtov rachmana
ubehera'ot bo, when it appears to him. Why does it have to
say on the day? מאי וביום, Mai uveyom, on the day? שמע
מינה יש יום שאתה רואה בו ויש יום שאי אתה רואה בו.
shema mina yesh yom she'ata roeh bo ve'yesh yom she'ei ata roeh
bo. It's telling you there are some days you see, some days
you don't. The whole word ביום beyom on the day is extra.
Okay, ואביי, ve'Abaye, what would אביי Abaye say? Why do you need
the word ביום? beyom? ההוא מבעיא ליה ביום ולא בלילה, hahu mibaya
lei beyom velo balailah,
day and not night. That's why it says ביום. beyom. And therefore
you have to focus on the extra ו' vav because ביום beyom
is needed to tell you you only look at the, look at
it in the daytime. ורבא, Ve'Rava, רבא Rava ביום ולא בלילה מנא
ליה? beyom velo balailah minalei?
Where did he get the idea that you only see the daytime
since he uses the whole word ביום beyom to tell you there's
a selection of days? So the גמרא Gemara says, נפקא ליה מכל
מראה עיני הכהן, nafka lei mikol marei einei hakohen, to the entire
vision of the appearance of to the eyes of the כהן, kohen,
which means that it has to be completely like visible, which is
a day, you know, it's a day that you can naturally see
without artificial light.
How do you get that?
It's מראה עיני הכהן, marei einei hakohen, what you can see. What
you can see means what you can see naturally, somehow he reads
it. Or maybe the full seeing, so there doesn't need to be
any other, any assistance to it. ואביי, Ve'Abaye, what does אביי Abaye
do with that verse? ההוא מבעיא ליה למיעוטי סומא באחת מעיניו, hahu
mibaya lei lemi'utei suma be'achat mei'einav,
to exclude a case of a כהן kohen who only has vision
in one eye. It has to be כל מראה עיניו, kol marei
einav, it has to be his full vision. So,
so that's what he learns from that verse. ורבא, Ve'Rava, or עיניים
einayim plural, ורבא נמי מבעיא ליה להכא. ve'Rava nami mibaya lei leihacha.
So doesn't רבא Rava need it for that? רבא Rava also presumably
wouldn't disagree on that פסק. psak. אין הכי נמי, Ein hachi nami,
you're right. ואלא ביום ולא בלילה מנא ליה? Ve'ela beyom velo balailah
minalei? So רבא Rava needs the verse to the full vision of
the eyes of the כהן kohen to tell you he has to
be sighted in both eyes, where does רבא Rava learn the idea
only at daytime since he uses the word ביום beyom to tell
you you select which day? So the גמרא Gemara says, ואלא ביום
ולא בלילה מנא ליה, ve'ela beyom velo balailah minalei, נפקא ליה מכנגע
נראה לי בבית, nafka lei mikinega nira li babayit,
like a spot appeared to me in the house is what the
person says to the כהן, kohen, and what's the דרשה? drasha? לי
ולא לאורי, li velo le'ori,
it appeared to me without any artificial assistance, assistance,
without any light, without any artificial light. It appeared directly to me.
I didn't need to use any light, any artificial light to help
me see. And that's how you know that it's, that it's there.
Of course this is what the person says to the כהן. kohen.
It's not telling you the circumstances under which. the כהן, Kohen, what
do you call it, under which the כהן Kohen comes and and
looks at it. You know, but nevertheless, presumably if the very, if
the person reporting, the non-expert, has to see it with without artificial
light presumably the כהן Kohen has to see it without artificial light.
Isn't this another way of דרשנינג darshening the פשט pshat that it
has to be during the daytime with the light coming into the
house from outside?
Right. Exactly. The אביי Abaye and אביי Abaye would say back, אי
מהתם הוה אמינא הני מילי טומאה דלאו דגופיה? im mahatam hava amina
hani milei tuma d'lav degufei? Sure, but that's a פסוק pasuk about
the house. So maybe when it comes to טומאה tuma not on
the body, it has to be by the light of the day.
אבל טומאה דגופיה אפילו לאור הנר נמי? aval tuma degufei afilu l'or
hanner nami? But by by טומאה tuma on the body, a spot
on the body maybe even by the light of a candle, which
is bizarre because we would normally think that's a weightier טומאה tuma
so it would have higher criteria, but may you know more demanding
criteria, but maybe the גמרא's Gemara saying no, because it's a weightier
טומאה tuma maybe we're more prepared to make it טמא. tamei. It'll
be easier to be טמא, tamei, we'll even do it you know
through other types you know through expanded ways. Anyway, קא משמע לן
kamashma lan not. So everybody gets the same thing, some have the
extra ו vav or the extra י, yud, ביום bayom tells you
there are days you see days you don't see, and as we
heard before, there is a potential debate of רבא Rava and אביי
Abaye
in understanding the debate of the תנאים Tannaim whether the תנאים Tannaim
were actually arguing that maybe you could even defer it based on
a non מצוה mitzvah reason and that you really have a good
degree of discretion when to see it when not to see it.
I should point out that what the גמרא Gemara has done here,
we shouldn't take completely for granted, in one way this is just
okay, this standard thing the גמרא Gemara does working through the פסוק
pasuk what do you do with this letter what do you do
with this word. But what's interesting is that the גמרא Gemara does
it here with אביי Abaye and רבא. Rava. And אביי Abaye and
רבא Rava you know are pretty darn late in the period of
the אמוראים. Amoraim. And we're usually used to the idea that the
אמוראים Amoraim interpret the תנאים Tannaim they don't directly דרשן darshen פסוקים.
pesukim. And even earlier you know they were אביי Abaye and רבא
Rava were discussing the debate of רבי Rabbi and who was it?
Whoever the תנא קמא Tanna Kama was, רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda and
רבי, Rabbi, and explaining their the the תנאים's Tannaim different approach to
the פסוקים. pesukim. And all of a sudden it became אביי Abaye
and רבא's Rava different approach to the פסוקים. pesukim. So that's quite
interesting sort of seeing the אמוראים Amoraim that
late involved in that degree of דרשנינג darshening the פסוקים. pesukim. But
again this is like a גמרא's Gemara reconstruction you know. So you
don't
you know it's hard to know exactly how much of this was
original אביי Abaye and רבא. Rava. Even the very originals even the
very initial statements right אמר אביי אם כן לכתוב רחמנא ביום מאי
וביום? amar Abaye im ken lichtov rachmana bayom mai ubayom? רבא אמר
כולה קרא יתירה היא. Rava amar kulla kra yeseira hi. Those are
all purely in Aramaic. And even when the אמוראים Amoraim speak when
they're directly quoted they usually speak in Hebrew not in Aramaic. So
one has to ask like how much of all of this presentation
was like a type of a reconstruction of what אביי Abaye and
רבא Rava said or an imagining of what אביי Abaye said. But
anyway it is interesting to note that that is that this approach
which we take for granted is being applied here to אביי Abaye
and רבא. Rava.
In any case that statement you just made in other words you're
saying that when there's discourse in Aramaic it's 90% primarily identifying the
סתם stam and when there are named אמוראים Amoraim we should look
to see that they're speaking Hebrew.
Well it's yes it's almost always I mean people are shocked when
they hear this. I ask them like what language did the אמוראים
Amoraim speak and everyone says
Aramaic. And the answer is no, the אמוראים Amoraim speak, I mean
I'm sure they spoke at home in
Aramaic, but when they spoke and issued statements for quotation it was
in Hebrew. And if you pay attention that's true the Aramaic of
the גמרא Gemara is the glue, the narrative that weaves together all
of the statements. Now the question is when they weren't giving apodictic
statements when they weren't just sort of saying this is the הלכה
halakha or the you know this is the case of the משנה
mishna or something like that you know when they were having more
of a back and forth discussion then yes that you know then
that might have been in Aramaic but then there is a question
about how much were those statements sort of you know shaped and
redacted for quotation and how much are they sort of capturing the
gist of what the debate was but they weren't actually statements that
were fashioned for quotation. So here the entire thing you don't even
start with a kernel that's in Hebrew. The entire thing you know
is in Aramaic. But anyway even if we imagine that there was
an initial issue of the אביי Abaye and רבא Rava of different
take on the word ביום וביום bayom ubayom still the elaboration of
it as what this vs this vs that vs this letter is
something that's clearly the גמרא Gemara is doing. Okay let's take a
look now at the משנה. mishna.
ועוד אמר רבי מאיר. V'od amar Rabbi Meir. So רבי מאיר Rabbi
Meir was the one that said before you can look at it
for to be lenient but not to be strict and רבי יוסי
Rabbi Yose said you don't look at it at all. So we're
going to have another debate of רבי מאיר Rabbi Meir and רבי
יוסי. Rabbi Yose. ועוד אמר רבי מאיר V'od amar Rabbi Meir רבי
מאיר Rabbi Meir also said מלקט אדם עצמות אביו ואמו מפני ששמחה
היא לו. melaket adam atzmos aviv v'imo mipnei shesimcha hi lo. A
person can gather the bones of his father and mother because it's
a joy for him. who are buried and they collect it for
reburial because that is a day of joy. What they used to
do is, I was reading one of the אחרונים acharonim speculates that
this is because so there shouldn't be like pockets of טומאה tumah
all over ארץ ישראל, Eretz Yisrael, but I think that the scholars
more believe that this is because of the scarcity of land in
Israel, maybe those are somewhat related. But anyway, they would bury the
body until the flesh would decompose, and then after the flesh would
decompose, because you know when you bury a body you need, you
know, six feet of land, six feet by two feet by however
deep, anyway after the flesh would decompose, gather up all the bones
and then you know you can sort of, you know, put them
in a nice tight dense package essentially, you know, gather them together,
and then you put them in the כוך, kuch, in the like
little sarcophagus or the you know little walls in a cave and
you would have the family cave, and you know each, and the
little holes and the little inserts would be the bones that you
had collected and that's all, you know, saves a lot of land
by doing it that way. And also according to this other idea
doesn't have things spread out all over Israel, a more, you know,
densely packed and centralized, and that's what they would do. And that
would be called ליקוט עצמות. likut atzamos. So, yes, is this like
the
when you see the Sanhedrin, you know, when you go to Jerusalem,
you just put a whole body into those
stone areas and then?
Yeah, you know G,
that was like the, this is the first step.
That is a good question. I definitely know that they did that
in some places, like in Rome and in other places, not Jews,
just סתם. stam. I just remember from years ago when I was
in Rome or whatever they would bury whole bodies into the walls
of caves. And maybe they did that sometimes as well. Maybe, you
know, maybe what Rabbi Dov is saying is right, like if you
have like a wealthy family maybe they did that. But a lot
of what they did was they buried and then and re-gather the
bones and put them, then the bones are nice and compact and
put those, you know, put those in the, what do you call
it, in the wall. Which also explains why sometimes in the laws
of טומאת מת tumas meis you see a discussion of like מלוא
תרווד רקב, melo taryad rekev, like a certain quantity of decomposed, you
know, dust from the dead body. Well, when, when do you ever
get decomposed dust of a dead body? Well, if you're opening up
the grave and taking out the bones, you might also have some
stuff that's there that's still, you know, not fully absorbed into the
ground.
Yes, and this ליקוט likut is, is the rabbinic equivalent in the
תנ"ך Tanakh as ויגוע אל עמיו, vayigva el amav, he was gathered
unto his
people, which was
the gathering of the bones to an ossuary.
But it's all mentioned at the same time though, ויגוע וימת ויאסף
אל עמיו. Vayigva vayamos vayayeisef el amav.
Yeah, ויגוע vayigva and then וימת.
vayamos.
That's what I remember reading that they think it's the פשט pshat
of the ויאסף אל עמיו. vayayeisef el amav. Maybe it's more the
ויאסף אל עמיו. vayayeisef el amav. ויאסף, vayeisef, so to be gathered
in means that after the body then you're gathered into the home,
to the family plot and ossuary. Could be interesting. Okay, so the
גמרא Gemara so anyway, רבי מאיר Rabbi Meir says look, you know,
they died a year ago or whenever they died, and now you
feel good, oh we get to move, you know, move the bones
into the family plot. So, now,
fine, that's true. רבי יוסי אומר, Rabbi Yose omer, this is a,
you know, hundred more years, a hundred years or more after the
חורבן הבית. churban habayis. So anyway, רבי יוסי אומר אבל הוא לו.
Rabbi Yose omer avel hu lo. No,
even, you know, look, they might have died more than a year
ago or more, but still you're re-encountering it, it's a day of
mourning. Okay. And therefore you can't do it. So again Rabbi Yose
is saying don't do these things on the רגל, regel, Rabbi Meir
is giving more latitude. It's hard to see how the two debates
are linked, but they are parallel. לא יספוד אדם על מתו, Lo
yispod adam al meiso, now presumably everybody agrees that a person should
not bestir himself over over a, you know, relative who has died.
We'll see in the גמרא. Gemara. ולא יספדנו, V'lo yispedenu, and should
not eulogize him קודם לרגל שלושים יום, kodem l'regel shloshim yom, thirty
days before the רגל. regel. Okay. So what does ולא יספדנו v'lo
yispedenu mean? Also what if somebody dies thirty days before the רגל?
regel? You can't give a eulogy? So we'll see, these are talking
about a much more public and emotional types of wailings that get
done. But let's first take a look, let's look at this one
by one. ורמינהו. U'reminhu. I'll ask you on this issue about that
gathering the bones is considered to be a שמחה simcha according to
Rabbi Meir. המלקט עצמות אביו ואמו, Hamelaqeit atzmos aviv v'imo, if somebody
gathers the bones of his father and mother, הרי זה מתאבל עליהם
כל היום, harei zeh misavel aleihem kol hayom, he mourns for them
the entire day, ולאור אינו מתאבל עליהם, v'la'or eino misavel aleihem, and
not at nighttime. But okay, nighttime isn't relevant. The point is, it's
an אבל avel for that day. ואמר רב חסדא, V'amar Rav Chisda,
רב חסדא Rav Chisda says, אפילו צרורין לו בסדינו, afilu tzrurin lo
b'sadino, even if it's wrapped in your like handkerchief. Now what does
that mean? So, you know, the רבינו גרשום Rabbeinu Gershom says here
means even if you don't see them, you still mourn for them
because even if they're covered up. תוספות Tosafos says it means that
even if it's no, he's not being strict, he's being lenient. It's
going on the idea you don't do it in the evening, even
if they haven't been reburied yet. You know, they're still wrapped up
in whatever, in whatever sort of a sheet you wrapped them in
to convey them. You haven't buried them yet, they're still waiting reburial,
but nevertheless by the evening you no longer have אבל. avel. The
אבל avel lasts only in the day, it does not go into
the night, even if they have not yet been reburied. Okay. So
the issue of the night and when, what, when they've been reburied
is irrelevant. What's relevant for us is the fact that That the
daytime is אבלות. Aveilus. How does it work with רבי מאיר? Rebbe
Meir? The גמרא Gemara says גמרא
סוף דף ס' עמוד ב'
Gemara
sof
daf samech amud beis or
I don't think so.
It's rarely translated. It really means shroud. Maybe I don't know that
would be anyway. ואמר אביי, V'amar Abaye, אביי Abaye says אימא Eima
מפני ש mipnei she
anyway the shroud would decompose faster than the what do you call
it I would imagine? I don't know. I actually don't know about
that. Anyway, ואמר אביי, V'amar Abaye, I'm sorry, אמר אביי: Amar Abaye:
אימא מפני ששמחת הרגל עליו. Eima mipnei she'simchas ha'regel alav.
So interestingly what the גמרא Gemara chooses to do is say you
know what רבי מאיר Rebbe Meir actually agrees that there would be
a day of אבל Evel during that transport. So what does רבי
מאיר Rebbe Meir mean when he says it's a שמחה simcha for
him? He says he didn't mean the reburying is a שמחה. simcha.
He means that because of the joy of the רגל, regel, you
don't get overwhelmed by the אבלות aveilus of the reburying. So that
you know it's not like it's so powerful, it's been a year
ago, so that emotion of אבלות aveilus is not you know there's
רבי מאיר Rebbe Meir admits that there's an element of אבלות aveilus
as we see, מתאבל עליהם כל היום, misabel aleihem kol hayom, but
that small element of אבלות aveilus is nothing you have to worry
about because what much more dominates for the person is the feeling
of שמחת הרגל. simchas ha'regel. Now that is a very difficult rereading.
First of all, a completely you know rereads what רבי מאיר Rebbe
Meir says in the משנה. mishna. He says it's a שמחה simcha
and that's contrasted to רבי יוסי Rebbe Yossi saying it's an אבל.
evel. But also if רבי מאיר Rebbe Meir agrees with this, so
imagine what we're saying. The person is נוהג מנהגי אבלות. noheig minhagei
aveilus. What do I care what you feel? He's נוהג מנהגי אבלות.
noheig minhagei aveilus. מתאבל עליהם Misabel aleihem is telling you he's נוהג
מנהג אבלות. noheig minhag aveilus. So how רבי מאיר Rebbe Meir saying,
"Yes, it's okay to be נוהג noheig a day of מנהג אבלות
minhag aveilus on the רגל regel since you're basically absorbed in having
joy of the רגל regel anyway?" Like it's very hard, not clear
at all how that logically makes sense. And you know and תוספות
Tosafos says if you just look at a little
תוספות Tosafos רמינהי המלקט עצמות Remini ha'melaiket atzamos תוספות Tosafos says במסכת
שמחות b'Masechet Smachos this is a ברייתא braisa from במסכת שמחות Masechet
Smachos which is a collection of Tannaic material relating to
אבלות. aveilus. הא מני רבי יוסי היא Ha mani Rebbe Yossi hi
דאמר משנה אינה לו. De'amar mishna einah lo. It's a ברייתא. braisa.
So this is רבי יוסי. Rebbe Yossi. רבי מאיר Rebbe Meir disagrees.
רבי יוסי Rebbe Yossi says it's אבל, evel, רבי מאיר Rebbe Meir
says it's שמחה. simcha. So it's very strange that the גמרא Gemara
feels that this is such a problem and the way it reconciles
it doesn't make much sense. You know and fine it's one thing
to say you don't get emotional but how could you admit that
it's an אבל evel there, הלכתית halachically you do אבל, evel, and
that what do you call it and that you're still allowed to
do it on the on the רגל. regel. So I don't know.
I don't have a good answer. A simpler answer is that's exactly
the debate of רבי מאיר Rebbe Meir and רבי יוסי. Rebbe Yossi.
Now we continue דלא
יערר על מתו D'lo ye'arer al meiso do not sort of bestir
yourself over a relative who has died. So מאי לא יערר על
מתו? mai lo ye'arer al meiso? What does this mean? אמר רב:
Amar Rav: כד הוי ספדנא במערבא kad havay safdana b'ma'arava when the
wailers you see we say a הספד hesped is a eulogy but
it's more like a wailing would be a more accurate translation, right?
And להספיד l'haspid means like to beat yourself, right? Like to bang
your breast or whatever. So when the wailers would circle around in
ארץ ישראל, Eretz Yisrael, אמרי amri they would say: יבכו עמו כל
מרירי לבי yivku imo kol merirei libi come cry with me all
people who are of embittered heart. So basically you would hire some
people and you would they would all go around and they'd try
to get the whole community wailing and stirred up and they'd go
door to door, "Come, oh my God, this person has died, let's
all wail and cry and it's a terrible thing," etc. etc. So
that's we'll get to that that's לא יערר lo ye'arer before thirty
days. And
לא יספדנו. lo yispodenu. The ריטב"א Ritva says it's not much different,
but לא יערר lo ye'arer means that the person has died maybe
earlier, maybe what you're doing for the הקמת מצבה. hakamas matzeiva. You're
hiring some new anyway. He says it's something that you're doing not
immediately after the death. Maybe the person has died a while ago
but you're going to do some now some big sending eulogizers around
and doing this whole thing. And לא יספדנו lo yispodenu is when
the person actually has died within thirty days and that's more of
a of a giving of a הספד hesped but again not just
a eulogy but a הספד hesped that's stirring people up. So let's
take a look. קודם לרגל שלשים יום. Kodem l'regel shloshim yom. So
why not? So מאי שנא שלשים יום? mai shna shloshim yom? Why
can't you do this thirty days before? אמר רב כהנה אמר רב
יהודה אמר רב: Amar Rav Kahana amar Rav Yehuda amar Rav: מעשה
באדם אחד Ma'aseh b'adam echad there's a story with a person, man,
שכינס מעות לעלות לרגל she'kinnes ma'os la'alos la'regel that he gathered money
to be עולה לרגל. oleh l'regel. ובא ספדן U'va safdan and one
of these eulogizers, wailers, came, וקם על פתח ביתו v'kam al pesach
beiso stood by
the opening of his house, door of his
house. ונתלהבה אשתו V'nisla'ava ishto and his wife was so worked up
and emotional over the you know with the wailing and the death
and the
crying. ונתנתן לו V'nasnan lo what did she do? She gave him
the money, right? Because apparently these people got paid. You know it's
sort of like excuse the analogy like the street performers in Central
Park. You know, "Oh, you like what you see, so you give
them some money." So these people are going around and wailing, the
people would give them some money. Okay, so that's what she
did. And he wasn't able to be עולה לרגל oleh laregel ואותה
שעה אמרו V'otah sha'ah amru
that time they said, which is again now over a hundred years
before the משנה Mishnah was being written, so it's funny that it's
linked but linked to this, לא יעורר על מתו ולא יספידנו קודם
לרגל שלשים יום Lo ye'orer al meto ve'lo yaspidennu kodem laregel shloshim
yom because this thing was done by professionals and because obviously people
would feel guilty and you'd have all this mourning and crying and
people would feel you have to contribute to show you're honoring the
dead. So it would basically draw on communal funds when people needed
that money before the רגל, regel, even if you're not being עולה
רגל, oleh regel, you need the money to make a nice יום
טוב. Yom Tov. So, and you can certainly understand the way this
pulls at heartstrings and is unfair in the way that it is
that it creates a sort of pressure, societal pressure and expectation to
be contributing at the time when people need to be using their
money for other things.
In the one person...
No, but it's a broader type of concern of this type of
a what this phenomenon was like and the type of response that
it engendered, that people want, it made people, you know, it put
it put pressure on people, you know, emotional, societal pressure to be
giving their money and that this is not the time to be
doing that.
שמואל אמר שמואל. Shmuel amar Shmuel. All right, שמואל אמר שמואל Shmuel
amar Shmuel says
שאין המת משתכח מן הלב שלשים יום. She'ein hamet mishtakach min halev
shloshim yom.
Maybe a more direct reason. He says, if you get all worked
up thirty days before, you're still thinking about it, you're still emotionally
distraught up to thirty days later. Now that's fascinating because normally we
say that means that thirty days after the person has died. Here,
even if the person hasn't, you know, you're still thinking about it,
you're not moving on yet. Here, if the person could have died
a while ago, but if you had this whole
major wailing that was done, that still emotionally weighs on you up
to thirty days later. And therefore it would not be appropriate for
שמחת הרגל. Simchat haregel. So מאי בינייהו, mai beinaihu, what's the difference
of these two approaches? איכא בינייהו דעביד בחנם. Ika beinaihu de'avid bechinam.
Let's say it's a society where these wailers are not being paid,
everything is being done for free. So therefore, you know, that would
so שמואל Shmuel would still face a problem because you're still left
with like the emotional baggage of this experience. Okay. But again, don't
translate that to mean that we don't do הספדים hespedim nowadays, because
a הספד hesped thirty days before we do. הספד Hesped there means
much more of this stirring everybody up, which is interesting because it
raises the question that at other times when we say you don't
do הספדים, hespedim, but you don't do הספדים hespedim all of ניסן,
Nissan, you know, and or you know, and those types of things.
You don't do הספדים hespedim on חול המועד Chol Hamoed or something.
Is that obvious that the הספד hesped the גמרא Gemara is talking
about and all of those limits apply to what we do? I
mean, we don't sort of, I mean every now and then people
cry a little bit, but we're not trying to get everybody emotional
and crying and wailing, which is what they were in the time
of the גמרא. Gemara. Yeah, you're trying more to be affirming the
positive of whatever. It's a very different goal and experience than it
was in the גמרא. Gemara. So it raises interesting questions because nobody
says you can't have a הספד hesped thirty days before the רגל,
regel, which is what the משנה Mishnah says. Okay, but we do
say you can't have הספדים hespedim at other times. Yes.
These guys are same as the מקוננות? mekonenot?
Yeah, they were slightly different. I thought, oh yeah, they were all
related to the same phenomenon. I don't get exactly the exact difference.
I think the מקוננות mekonenot more were doing like a public, a
poetic
scripted dirge whereas these people were trying to just get everybody to
start crying. But anyway.
Which we think we can't, we say הלכה halacha now, we still
do make a הספד hesped in thirty days, but we don't do
it on the רגל. regel.
Yeah, and we also don't do it like all of ניסן Nissan
and obviously we can't bifurcate that.
Yeah, I think
that's what I'm raising, it's a good question why we make that
split. Okay, אין חופרין כוכין ein hofrin kuchin back to burying them
or staying with burying them. You do not dig these כוכין, kuchin,
these you know these what are they called these sarcophagi, is that
what it's called? No, it's no, no, no, they're the holes in
the cave.
Crypt? But they build the crypt and then they have recesses.
Recesses. It's the hole in the crypt. Okay.
Or burial niches.
Niches. Oh, that's a good word. Okay, so you don't dig these
niches קבורות kevurot or the or graves במועד be'moed on חול המועד.
Chol Hamoed. Okay, so the quest well the question of course is
but let's say the guy died on חול המועד. Chol Hamoed. Okay,
so we'll talk about that in a minute. אבל מחנכין את הכוכין
במועד, aval mechanchin et hakoachin bemoed, you can you can arrange these
niches on חול המועד. Chol Hamoed. You can like fix them up,
but you can't dig them fresh. ועושים נברכת במועד, ve'osim nivrechet bemoed,
you can make a little pool of water on חול המועד. Chol
Hamoed. Now what's that for? So רבינו גרשום Rabbeinu Gershom says it's
for doing laundry
and תוספות Tosafot says why are you doing laundry on חול המועד?
Chol Hamoed? So it says well there's some people that are allowed
to do laundry, but תוספות Tosafot then has a good has another
alternative suggestion which is keeping it in the theme of of dead
bodies and he says that you're doing it to bathe the the
body, you know, to do the טהרה. taharah. Okay, but you can
so you can make this little pool pond of water וארון עם
המת בחצר ve'aron im hamet bechatzer and תוספות Tosafot that read is
much makes much more sense because it's all about the dead body
and you can also build the coffin the
coffin if the dead body is in the yard when you're building
the coffin. Okay? Because otherwise people see a guy in his workshop
with wood and banging his hammer and nails and they have no
idea what the heck he's doing.
No, they don't, that's the problem. So it has to be done
in a context where it's clear that you're making the coffin.
You need a sign: coffin maker.
Exactly. One does wonder other things that might help for the context.
רבי יהודה אוסר אלא אם כן יש לו נסרים. Rebbi Yehuda oser
ela im kein yeish lo nesarim. Rebbi Yehuda has another restriction. You
cannot be planing, is that what it's called? Planing new planks of
wood. You cannot be making planks of wood, that would be doing
too much from scratch, too much effort. You have to go ahead
and use existing planks. Now of course the question here is: Okay,
it's all very nice to give those restrictions, but let's say according
to Rebbi Yehuda you didn't have any planks of wood. What are
you supposed to do? Not bury the guy for all of חול
המועד? Chol HaMoed? Bury him without a coffin? Let's say you didn't
have a hole in your... you know, in your thing, what are
you supposed to do? So some ראשונים Rishonim read at least the
first statement of not making the niches and not making graves is
only if you're doing it in advance. You're doing it, you know,
the guy isn't dead yet, you're preparing it for, you know, for
the future when somebody will die. That's what you can't do, but
if the guy's actually dead, then of course if you need a
grave, you bury a grave. Okay, but okay, it doesn't answer the
last question. Let's say there's no coffin and you don't have planks
of wood, what are you supposed to do? So, you know, it's
not addressed in the גמרא. Gemara. One imagines obviously you find some
alternative. Either, you know, maybe it means that okay, there is an
alternative but it's not ideal, it's very expensive, etc. And if there's
literally no alternative, one imagines it would be allowed. But again, how
to deal with the reality of if you actually have a dead
body and you don't have the ability to bury and you've got
these restrictions, what are you going to do now? That is not
explicitly addressed in the משנה Mishnah or the גמרא. Gemara.
When is it spoken in the... I think they quoted it in
Israel at some point... for the body to be wrapped up? Right,
right.
Right, without it. Right. Yes, so I don't know. It's a good
question. I imagine
also... I don't know the answer to that. It's a very good
question. Yeah, you're right, because sometimes it's assuming with a coffin and
sometimes without.
Also could be that the coffin is used for conveyance, you know,
bringing the body out to the... that's often referred to as the
מיטה, mitah, the bed, you know, or the bier, but often there's
a bringing of the body out and then there's the burying of
the body. I guess if it was only used for conveyance, you
wouldn't have to make a new one each time, you'd have one.
Yeah. Okay. כוכין וקברות, kuchin u'kvaros, where are these niches and graves?
אמר רב יהודה כוכין בחפירה וקברות בבנין. Amar Rav Yehuda kuchin b'chafira
u'kvaros b'vinyan. Kuchin are things you
dig and kvaros are things in a structure. Now, it's funny, I
would think the opposite. Kuchin are normally things you assume that are
in a cave and the קבר kever something you normally assume is
in the ground. I didn't exactly get it. תניא נמי הכי אלו
הן כוכין ואלו הן קברות כוכין בחפירה וקברות בבנין. Tanya nami hachi
elu hein kuchin v'elu hein kvaros kuchin b'chafira u'kvaros b'vinyan. Okay. So
I don't know, maybe the notes say something about that, but I
didn't really understand that. Okay, אבל מחנכין את הכוכין, aval mechanchin es
ha'kuchin, you can arrange the kuchin as opposed to digging them fresh.
So היכי מחנכין, heichi mechanchin, how would you arrange it? אמר רב
יהודה שאם היתה אורך מקצרו. Amar Rav Yehuda she'im haysa orech mekatzro.
If it was too long, you could make it shorter. ובמתניתא תניא
מאריך בו ומרחיב בו. u'v'masnisa tanya maarich bo u'marchiv bo. The opposite:
you can make it longer, you can make it wider. So you
can... we've seen this before in other types of contexts: you can
fix something that's already there but you don't make it fresh. ועושין
נברכת, v'osin nivrechet, you make a pool of water. מאי נברכת? Mai
nivrechet? אמר רב יהודה זו בקעא, Amar Rav Yehuda zu bika, which
apparently means a pool of water. Okay, והתניא v'hatanya we taught in
a ברייתא, Braisa, הנברכת והבקעא, ha'nivrechet v'ha'bika, so clearly they're two different
things.
So
it says, אמר אביי ואיתימא רב כהנא גיהו ובר גיהו. Amar Abaye
v'isayma Rav Kahana geihu u'var geihu. There's a main one and there's
a secondary one. You'd make a main one and then you'd make
a smaller one where the water would run off to. Somehow they
would both sort of be serving some type of a purpose. Okay.
Now, fine. Where are we?
וארון עם המת בחצר. v'aron im ha'meis b'chatzer. תנינא להא דתנו רבנן,
Tanina l'ha d'sanu rabbanan, we taught in our mishnah what the rabbis
teach in a ברייתא. Braisa. עושין כל צרכי המת. Osin kol tzorchei
ha'meis. You do anything you need for the dead body. גוזמין לו
שערו, Gozmin lo se'aro, you cut the hair. ומכבסין לו כסותו, u'mechabsin
lo kesuso, you launder the clothes. This means the
shrouds. ועושין לו ארון מנסרים המנוסרים מערב יום טוב. v'osin lo aron
m'nesarim ha'menusarim m'erev Yom Tov. And you can make a coffin from
pre-made planks, planks that were made ערב יום טוב. erev Yom Tov.
So that's a limitation though, it has to be pre-made planks, right?
Which is interesting because there's other... you know, there's other things that
say you can even weave his shroud. So what's the difference between
weaving a shroud and making planks? But maybe there is a difference,
not just in terms of effort, that's partly, but also in terms
of people, you know, it's very loud when people hear the carpentry
and all of that type of a thing and people also imagine,
you know, if they see all this carpentry being done that it's
for some big project. They don't... so the issue about it sort
of being public and people perceiving, you know, that you're doing... making
these planks. So that is the limit set in the תנא קמא,
Tanna Kamma, in our משנה Mishnah that was רבי יהודה, Rabbi Yehuda,
and here we have the opposing voice of רבן שמעון בן גמליאל
אומר אף מביאים עצים ומנסרים בצינעה בתוך ביתו. Rabban Shimon ben Gamliel
omer af mevi'im etzim u'menasrim b'tzina b'toch beito. No, even if you
need to, you can make the planks as long as you do
it in private in your house. One wonders if you have to
have the מת Meis in your house when you're doing the planks;
presumably no. Presumably when you're in the חצר Chatzer and people are
seeing you, you need the מת Meis there to provide the context.
When you're doing the planks, which is even more problematic, that you
do בצינעה B'tzina in your house, but presumably there you don't need
the מת Meis because it's in private. תוספות Tosafot raises an interesting
question: normally we don't distinguish private and public, we say it's all
the same, מראית העין. Maris Ayin. Here we do distinguish, and one
of the interesting things to think about in terms of that, the
difference of, right—do people understand the question? I'm saying this pretty fast—but
why should it make a difference private or public is that it's
not necessarily מראית העין, Maris Ayin, it's more about impinging on the
character of יום טוב Yom Tov or חול המועד, Chol HaMoed, right?
So there's for example issues of that you don't have like non-Jews
working in your house on שבת Shabbos even if they're basically not
paid a daily wage and they're contracted and they're choosing when to
work—I'm not telling them to work on שבת. Shabbos. So why not?
So one reason is מראית העין; Maris Ayin; people are going to
think you hired them דווקא Davka to work on שבת. Shabbos. But
another explanation has nothing to do with מראית העין, Maris Ayin, has
to do with the fact that work is going on in my
house on שבת, Shabbos, and that impacts the experience of שבת Shabbos
for me and for the community and for the, you know, and
the whole sort of nature of it as a day that we're
not doing any work. It doesn't matter technically whether there's a problem
or whether people interpret or misinterpret it; it's at the experiential level.
So here too, you know, to what degree does doing a whole
banging and making planks and the whole carpentry, does that impact the
whole experience of חול המועד? Chol HaMoed? So that could be why
maybe it's a difference in public or in private. So if you
have to make the planks, make them in private, but the other
part you can do in public, but again there have the מת
Meis there, have it give that type of a context. Okay, so
here's those different issues with certain limits though we normally have a
lot of latitude. And again though, the interesting question about what happens
if you have no choices, what are you supposed to do? So
before we move on to the next משנה, Mishnah, I want to
just quickly refer to two points in תוספות. Tosafot. This תוספות אין
חופרין, Tosafot Ein Chofrin, so first we'll do the point at the
end, which is the issue about that we maybe we're just assuming
that there's obviously alternatives. He says like this, he says: והא דשרינן
בפרק קמא דביצה—you V'ha d'sharinan b'perek kama d'beitzah see like at six
lines before the end where the parentheses are there—דף ו', Daf Vav,
למיגז גלימא ואסא. Limigaz glima v'asa. We allow you even to like
make new clothes for new shrouds. היינו דפשיטא שלא ימצא גלימא ואסא
עשויים מערב יום טוב, Hainu d'pishitah shelo yimtzah glima v'asa asuyim me'erev
Yom Tov, that you have no other alternative. אבל כוכין וקברות—so Aval
kuchin u'kvarot why do we not let you dig graves? ימצא הרבה—there
Yimtza harbeh you have a lot of options, even if you don't
dig the ones you want to be digging. דשכיחי ורגילין לחפור מחיים.
D'sh'chichi v'ragilin lachpor mechayim. מאי טעמא יהיה מותר בזמן הזה? Mai ta'ama
yihiyeh mutar b'zman hazeh? And then תוספות Tosafot says: ah, so if
that's why we're restricting it in the משנה, Mishnah, because the assumption
is that even if we restrict these things you have alternatives, so
maybe nowadays things are different. לפי שאין עושים כוכין וקברות מחיים. L'fi
she'ein osim kuchin u'kvarot mechayim. Nowadays well we don't have pre-dug graves
and we don't have alternatives, so maybe these things will be allowed.
So תוספות Tosafot explains that the restrictions in the משנה Mishnah were
only assuming that you had alternatives and that was a reality at
that time. But if we don't have alternatives, so obviously you gotta
bury the guy, you gotta bury the body, so those things will
be allowed. Now I do want to point out there's another fascinating
הוה אמינא Hava Amina in תוספות Tosafot which he completely rejects, but
it's still fascinating as a הוה אמינא Hava Amina because he's—you know
what the הלכה Halacha is, is that on the second day of
יום טוב Yom Tov there's a הלכה Halacha of עושין כל צרכי
המת, Osin kol tzorchei hameis, right? You even, you know, even Jews
can do anything you need for a dead body on the second
day of יום טוב. Yom Tov. Yeah, and he even says you
can weave the shrouds and all these types of things. So תוספות
Tosafot says: wait, if you look at that list, at least prima
facie it looks like we're giving even more latitude to things that
you can do on the second day יום טוב Yom Tov than
things you can do on חול המועד, Chol HaMoed, which is crazy.
So then he basically—the answer is like we'd think—he says: no, no,
they're basically all of the same level and it's the same allowance.
But he has a הוה אמינא Hava Amina to say maybe we
give you more latitude on the second day יום טוב Yom Tov
than we do on חול המועד. Chol HaMoed. Why? Because he says
if you take a look at what he says here at the
top, he says like this: אבל לצורך המת כמת כבר—it's Aval l'tzorech
hameis k'meis kvar like four lines down in the narrow lines from
the top here—מותר אפילו ביום טוב שני למיגז גלימא Mutar afilu b'Yom
Tov sheni limigaz glima to cut the garment ולמיגז אסא u'limigaz asa
כדאמרינן בפרק קמא דביצה. k'diamrinan b'perek kama d'beitzah. And if you're allowed
to do those things for the person who's already dead on second
day יום טוב, Yom Tov, קל וחומר חול המועד. Kal v'chomer Chol
HaMoed. Now he says: wait a minute, maybe we could say things
are allowed on the second day יום טוב Yom Tov that are
not allowed on חול המועד. Chol HaMoed. How could that be? דאף
על פי שיש לחלק דחול המועד דאורייתא יום טוב שני דרבנן. D'af
al pi she'yesh l'chaleik d'Chol HaMoed d'Oraisa Yom Tov sheni d'Rabbanan. Now
that should hit you as a shock, right? Because until now we've
been dealing with חול המועד Chol HaMoed as like... טרחא *tircha*, דרבנן
*rabbinic*. תוספות Tosafos *Tosafos* here introduces a very different voice: חול המועד
chol hamoed, *Chol Hamoed* is biblical, and יום טוב Yom Tov שני
*Yom Tov Sheni* is דרבנן *rabbinic*. So maybe we're actually more lenient
on יום טוב שני *Yom Tov Sheni* than on חול המועד chol
hamoed *Chol Hamoed*. There's only a little bit of a problem which
is what? יום טוב שני *Yom Tov Sheni* is also חול המועד
chol hamoed *Chol Hamoed*. הא *Ah*, but there's a יום טוב שני
*Yom Tov Sheni* that isn't חול המועד chol hamoed, *Chol Hamoed* at
the back end. Right. So he says, וכמו יום טוב שני דעצרת
ויום טוב שני דשביעי של פסח ושמיני עצרת *ve-kemo Yom Tov Sheni
d'Atzeret ve-Yom Tov Sheni d'Shevi'i shel Pesach ve-Shemini Atzeret*. Okay, he means
not שמיני עצרת *Shemini Atzeret* but שמחת תורה *Simchat Torah*, the יום
טוב שני *Yom Tov Sheni* of שמיני עצרת *Shemini Atzeret*. אי נראה
*ein nira*. That doesn't make sense. וכל יום שני קל וכו' *ve-chol
yom sheni kal ve-cho*? וכל המלאכה חמור טפי ביום טוב שני מחול
המועד *ve-chol ha-melacha chamur tefei be-Yom Tov Sheni mi-Chol Hamoed*. Okay, no,
give me a break. מלאכה melacha *melacha* is always more strict on
יום טוב שני *Yom Tov Sheni* than חול המועד chol hamoed? *Chol
Hamoed*. But it's a fascinating הוה אמינא *hava amina*, especially since we've
been used to seeing חול המועד Chol HaMoed, *Chol Hamoed* until this
point treated as דרבנן *d'Rabbanan*, טרחא *tircha*, and תוספות Tosafos *Tosafos* here
saying that that's דאורייתא *d'Oraisa* and in some ways maybe even weightier
than יום טוב שני *Yom Tov Sheni* at the end of the
חג chag *chag*. Okay, but then he rejects it, but it's still
a fascinating הוה אמינא *hava amina*. So the פשט *pshat* is though
that תוספות Tosafos *Tosafos* says, putting aside that interesting חול המועד Chol
HaMoed. יום טוב שני *Chol Hamoed Yom Tov Sheni*, maybe these cases
are all cases where we find more allowance other places in the
גמרא Gemara. *Gemara* and maybe the difference is about whether it's really
necessary or not. And the restrictions here are because it wasn't absolutely
necessary and therefore arguing that in his time when it was absolutely
necessary that therefore these restrictions would not apply. Can I answer? Can
I answer מר עין *Mar Ayin* was what? You know because you
said, oh, why is it? I'd say that it's not about מראית
עין *maris ayin*, it's more about the impact on the experience of
יום טוב *Yom Tov*. One other point where תוספות Tosafos *Tosafos* gives
a leniency is the fact that you need the dead body to
be in the courtyard when you're making the coffin to provide the
context. So if you take a look at תוספות Tosafos *Tosafos*, הארון
והמת בחצר *ha-aron ve-ha-mes be-chatzer*, תוספות *Tosafos* says אמינא בירושלמי *amina b'Yerushalmi*
אמר רב Rav. מנא *amar Rav Mana* הדא דאמר במת שאינו מפורסם
*hada d'amar be-mes she-eino mefursam*. That's only if it's not publicly known
that somebody had died. אבל במת מפורסם *aval be-mes mefursam*, if it's
well-known and public that somebody had died, עושין לו ארון אפילו בשוק
*osin lo aron afilu ba-shuk*, then you can do it in public
because people know you're making a coffin. They don't suspect, the fact
that it's well-known that somebody died gives context to what you're doing.
כי הא דרבי חנינא חבריה דרבנן דמך בחול המועד *ki ha de-Rabbi
Chanina chavreih de-rabbanan damach be-Chol Hamoed*, like Rabbi Chanina, one of a
colleague of the rabbis died on חול המועד Chol HaMoed. *Chol Hamoed*,
עבדי ליה ארון בשוקא *avdi lei aron be-shuka*, he made the coffin
even in the marketplace in a big public, not only חצר *chatzer*,
חצר *chatzer* is the yard of the courtyard. Here it was in
the marketplace, but it's okay, the context, everybody knew, it was very
public that this person had died. And therefore תוספות *Tosafos* says, ונראה
לן *ve-nira lan* ששיכלות מועטין *she-shichlut mu'atin*, we have very small communities,
חשיבי ליה מפורסם לכולי עלמא *chashivi lei mefursam le-chulei alma*, when anybody
dies everybody knows about it. Maybe you could say nowadays that we
have phone trees and everybody gets a phone call. But anyway, so
again our reality is different, we have small communities, you always have
the context. So two ways תוספות *Tosafos* is saying our reality is
different. Everybody knows and you always have context, that allows making the
ארון *aron* without having the מת *mes* physically present. And also if
we don't have alternatives and there's no way else to bury the
person or to make the coffin, then we're going to do it
anyway. Yes, it just seems though that you're, oh yeah, you have
the מת *mes* in with you in the חצר *chatzer*. Isn't it
a little, isn't that בזיון המת *bizayon ha-mes* slightly and is it
wherever you would go keep the מת *mes*? I mean if you
imagine that it's, I was wondering about that, like מת *mes* in
the חצר *chatzer* and how long does it take to make the
ארון *aron*? Yeah,
I mean if you imagine like a funeral home you could imagine
where they're keeping the מת *mes* is near where they're building the
ארון *aron*. But you're right, the way it's described is a little
strange. All right, let's take a look now. So on a shift
from אבילות *aveilus* issues, we shift to שמחה simcha. *simcha* issues, which
somewhat unexpectedly or not because people are probably familiar with the הלכות
*halachos*, but still we should allow ourselves to be surprised by the
fact that not only are you not allowed to do אבילות *aveilus*
issues on חול המועד Chol HaMoed, *Chol Hamoed*, you can't do שמחה
simcha. *simcha* issues either. Let's take a look. אין נושאין נשים במועד
*ein nosin nashim ba-moed*. A person does not, men, which is always
the implied subject, do not marry women on חול המועד Chol HaMoed,
*Chol Hamoed*. נושאין *nosin* means חופה *chuppah*, which means they're going to
start living together. It doesn't just the formal קידושין *kiddushin* with the
ring, which contractually makes them married, but the actual living together which
is the שמחה simcha *simcha*, which is why
שבע ברכות sheva brachos *Sheva Brachos* only come for the חופה *chuppah*
for the second part of the wedding because the שבע ברכות *Sheva
Brachos* is the expression of the joy of the חתן וכלה *choson
ve-kallah*, which come when the חתן וכלה *choson ve-kallah* actually come together
physically as a couple. Okay, and that's where the real שמחה simcha.
*simcha* is. סעודת נישואין *seudas nisuin* is always considered a סעודת מצוה
*seudas mitzvah* and שמחה simcha. *simcha* related, where סעודת אירוסין *seudas eirusin*
not. So interesting, I mean you always might get happy and you
drink and you have a good time, but in terms of like
a real סעודת מצוה *seudas mitzvah* and really identified as like a
שמחה simcha. *simcha* meal, that's סעודת נישואין *seudas nisuin* and that's שבע
ברכות *Sheva Brachos* and that's the נישואין *nisuin* event and it's not
the אירוסין *eirusin* event. So אין נושאין נשים במועד *ein nosin nashim
ba-moed*, so one does not actually get married, have the חופה *chuppah*
on חול המועד Chol HaMoed. *Chol Hamoed*. ולא בתולות ולא אלמנות, not
for women who are virgins, not even for second weddings, a woman
who is an אלמנה, almana, because there still is an aspect of
שמחה. simcha ולא מיבמין v'lo meyabmin and you don't do יבום, yibbum,
even though, you know, it's not a woman that you sort of
were dating or were like interested in and pursuing, it just happened
that you had to go out and do it because the brother
died and whatever, so maybe you'll say it's more like a of
a of an obligation than a real שמחה. simcha, No, you're still
getting married, you're still going to become one as a couple, God
willing you should have many kids and it should be a joyous
wedding מפני ששמחה היא לו. mipnei she-simcha hi lo. So interesting, right?
Quoting רבי מאיר's Rabbi Meir line, you have to appreciate the irony.
רבי מאיר Rabbi Meir said you could do ליקוט עצמות likud atzamos
מפני ששמחה היא לו. mipnei she-simcha hi lo. That's what allowed you
to do ליקוט עצמות likud atzamos here. Here it's saying you can't
do these things מפני ששמחה היא לו. mipnei she-simcha hi lo. So
here again we have the irony that שמחה simcha makes it not
allowed. אבל מחזיר הוא את גרושתו, aval machzir hu es grushaso, a
person can remarry a woman he divorced, because that's not such a
שמחה. simcha Alright, which is interesting. You know, trying again, but maybe
there's a lot of hesitation and concerns, and it's not something new
and fresh. Alright, somebody once said, said, who was it? I think
it was
Ben Johnson said about a second wedding, about about a second marriage,
he says it's the triumph of hope over experience. So anyway, alright,
so ועושה אשה תכשיטיה במועד, v'oseh isha tachshiteha b'moed, a woman to
do her makeup on חול המועד, and we'll see what that means.
רבי יהודה אומר Rabbi Yehuda omer לא תסוד lo sasud no, what
you cannot do is plaster her face, you know, with the way
of like removing the hair, you know, they still have things like
that nowadays, מפני שניוול הוא לה, mipnei she-nivvul hu lah, because even
though the goal is to look beautiful, in the process it's disgusting.
So therefore, you know, it's like the people putting on these like
mud packs on them, you know, on the Dead Sea or whatever.
So okay, might be in the end it's a nice result, but
it's a disgusting, it's not appropriate to חול המועד to be engaged
in that process. ההדיוט תופר כדרכו, ha-hedyot tofer k'darko,
a layperson can sew. Now finally we're getting to, well I don't
know finally we're getting to, you know until now we had been
dealing with like oh you can do things for דבר האבד, davar
ha'avad, right, for הפסד, hefsed, and now we're doing problems of אבלות,
avelus, problems of שמחה. simcha Now we're finally getting to some discussion
of the parameters of what type of a מלאכה is problematic on
חול המועד or not. Not just like exceptions of דבר האבד davar
ha'avad or broad concerns of אבלות avelus or שמחה. simcha. So ההדיוט
תופר כדרכו, ha-hedyot tofer k'darko, a layperson can sew normally, like, you
know, stitch up a button or a cut in their garment והאומן
מכלי. v'ha-uman machli. What? It's
a repair, yeah, והאומן מכלי, v'ha-uman machli, but we'll see, we'll see,
a craftsperson has to do a special type of a stitch, has
to do it in an unusual way, and we'll discuss what that
is in the גמרא. Gemara. ומסרגין את המטות umesargin es ha-mitos and
you can do sort of weave the beds, רבי יוסי אומר מותחין,
Rabbi Yossi omer mischin, you stretch them. So in terms of like
the ropes that would support the bed, we'll see all of this
in the גמרא. Gemara. But here you're actually getting to, again, appreciate
what we're looking at, we're getting to not just an allowance like
דבר האבד, davar ha'avad, we're getting to actually trying to define what
are the activities that are or are not problematic on חול המועד,
and so that's going to be, you know, obviously a key question
that we have not really explored yet. Let's take a look at
the גמרא. Gemara וכי שמחה היא לו מאי הוי, v'chi simcha hi
lo mai hovei, so what do I care that you have some
joy on חול המועד? Why should you not do things that are
joyous? So אמר רב יהודה אמר שמואל amar Rav Yehuda amar Shmuel
וכן אמר רבי אלעזר אמר רבי יאשיה v'chen amar Rabbi Elazar amar
Rabbi Yoshia ואמרי לה אמר רבי אלעזר אמר רבי חנינא v'amri lah
amar Rabbi Elazar amar Rabbi Chanina לפי שאין מערבין שמחה בשמחה. lefi
she-ein mearvin simcha b'simcha. A line that everybody knows, you don't mix
up one joyous event with another. Okay, we'll talk about that in
a minute. רבה בר בר חנה אמר Rabba bar bar Chuna amar
מפני שמניח שמחת הרגל ועושה בשמחת אשתו. mipnei she-maniach simchas ha-regel v'oseh
b'simchas ishto. You abandon the שמחת הרגל simchas ha-regel which is less
personal, right? It's a regel, everybody's happy on the regel, and you
focus on your personal שמחה simcha and therefore that compromises the שמחת
הרגל. simchas ha-regel. Now that sounds pretty similar to אין מערבין שמחה
בשמחה ein mearvin simcha b'simcha except that the concern here is specifically
about one side of the equation, abandoning שמחת הרגל, simchas ha-regel, right?
Whereas אין מערבין שמחה בשמחה ein mearvin simcha b'simcha the גמרא Gemara
conflates these and treats them as essentially the same reason, but אין
מערבין שמחה בשמחה ein mearvin simcha b'simcha is more general, right? It
could say like, no, I treat these both as important and I'm
not going and I'm going to engage myself in both, and nevertheless
אין מערבין שמחה בשמחה ein mearvin simcha b'simcha is basically saying, you
know, like you can't give each one the treatment that it deserves
if you're trying to engage in both of them at the same
time. So it's not like you're consciously ignoring one and focusing on
the other. You might merely be trying to do both in a
serious way, but you're not being fair to either one if you're
trying to do both at the same time. So it's a slightly
different issue. If you take a look תוספות sort of says it
לפי שאין מערבין שמחה בשמחה lefi she-ein mearvin simcha b'simcha תוספות says
גזירת הכתוב כדידרשינן לקמן מקודש. gezeras ha-kasuv k'didarshinan lekaman mi-kodesh. ומבירושלמי U-bi-Yerushalmi
דריש darash מדכתיב mide-ksiv מלא שבוע זאת. malei shavua zos. Right? First
get finished marrying לאה Leah and
then we’ll give you רחל. Rachel. Okay? והטעם יראה קצת Ve-hatam yereh
ketzas דכמו שאין עושין מצות חבילות חבילות, de-kemoshein osin mitzvos chavilos chavilos,
you don’t do mitzvos bundles, you don’t do two mitzvos at the
same time, you don’t multitask mitzvos. שצריך שיהיה לבו פנוי למצוה אחת
she-tzarich she-yiheh libo panuy le-mitzvah achas ולא יפנה עצמו הימנה. ve-lo yifneh
atzmo heimena. You need to focus on one thing at a
time. Okay? This is about anti-multitasking.
וכן שמחה בשמחה Ve-chein simcha be-simcha יהא לבו פנוי בשמחה. ye-he libo
panuy be-simcha. So it’s not like you abandon one for the other.
You try genuinely to do both, but that’s the problem. You’re not
going to do them as the way they need if you’re trying
to do two at the same time. Yeah?
So wouldn’t that mean he should get married like a day or
two before?
So we’ll actually talk about that a little. Okay. So we’re going
to talk about that. All right. You know we’ll talk about that
a little. Okay, so let’s take a look. אמר ליה אביי לרב
יוסף Amar lei Abaye le-Rav Yosef הא דרב בר רב הונא, Ha
de-Rabba bar Rav Huna, that statement of רב בר רב הונא Rav
bar Rav Huna that you abandon the רגל regel and you focus
on your wife, so meaning
דרב הוא, de-Rav hu, based on the statement of רב. דאמר רב
דניאל בר קטינא אמר רב De-amar Rav Daniel bar Katina amar Rav
מניין שאין נושאין נשים במועד, minayin she-ein nosin nashim be-moed, how do
you know you don’t marry women on חול המועד, שנאמר she-ne’emar ושמחת
בחגך ve-samachta be-chagecha בחגך ולא באשתך. be-chagecha ve-lo be-ishtecha. Again a focusing
of the competition of wife and חג as not a generic שמחה
בשמחה. simcha be-simcha. עולא אמר מפני הטורח. Ulla amar mipnei ha-torach. עולא
Ulla gives a very different reason.
You can have joy for other reasons on חול המועד. Problem is
that weddings require a lot of effort. You know, caterers and planning
and all that type of stuff and it’s too much effort for
on חול המועד. It’s like טירחא. tircha. Okay? Of course what does
the גמרא Gemara mean? Because of שמחה היא לו, simcha hi lo,
it means that because it’s such a שמחה, you’re going to be
investing a lot of effort. But it’s really about the effort, which
is not what the משנה Mishnah sounds like, but okay. רבי יצחק
נפחא אמר מפני ביטול פריה ורביה. Rabbi Yitzchak Nafcha amar mipnei bittul
piryah ve-rivyah. Now it’s because if you tell me I can get
married on חול המועד, like in the Ashkenazi terms in the Middle
Ages Ashkenazim they got married on ערב שבת. Erev Shabbos. You know
why? So they wouldn’t have to spend for two big meals. You’re
anyway having a big meal for שבת, Shabbos, so you have the
wedding on Friday late afternoon and then the שבת Shabbos meal is
the wedding feast. Show how poor they were. So you’re going to
say, what am I going to bake a big huge meal for
the wedding? I’ll wait till the רגל. regel. Anyway all my guests
are all my relatives are coming in anyway, I’m making that part
up, but okay, and I have to make a big meal, so
I’ll double it up. Okay? And therefore what you’re going to do,
so what’s the problem? If there’s not a problem of שמחה בשמחה,
simcha be-simcha, problem is that you really should would otherwise have married
six months ago or three months ago. So you’re postponing your marriage
for three months. That’s not appropriate. Now the גמרא Gemara. frames it
as ביטול פריה ורביה, bittul piryah ve-rivyah, postponing the possibility of having
kids. Okay, but the point is that’s the concern, not that there’s
really a competition with the רגל. regel. Also it’s hard to read
that into the משנה. Mishnah. That’s the reason he gives. Let’s take
a look a little bit in the גמרא. מיתיבי, Meisivei, let me
ask on this. כל אלו שאמרו אסור לישא במועד, Kol elu she-amru
asur lisa be-moed, all the people they said you can’t get married
on חול המועד, מותר לישא בערב הרגל. mutar lisa be-erev ha-regel. You
can get married ערב הרגל. Erev HaRegel. There you go Michael. קשיא
לכולהו. Kashya le-kulhu. It’s difficult for all of them. So שמחה will
stretch into the מועד, moed, the effort is going to be presumably
during the שבע ברכות as well, right? And the postponing is going
to occur, so it should also be אסור asur on ערב הרגל.
Erev HaRegel. So למאן דאמר משום שמחה, le-man de-amar mishum simcha, no,
עיקר שמחה חד יומא הוא, ikar simcha chad yoma hu,
the real שמחה is the day of the wedding. So if you
do it ערב erev the wedding it won't compete ערב רגל Erev
Regel it won't compete with the רגל. regel. למאן דאמר משום טירחא,
Le-man de-amar mishum tircha, if the issue is effort, עיקר טירחא חד
יומא הוא. ikar tircha chad yoma hu. Most of the effort is
on the first day of the wedding and that’ll be happen ערב
רגל. Erev Regel. You could also say, but it compromises your preparing
for the רגל, regel, but okay, נו נו. nu nu. למאן דאמר
משום ביטול פריה ורביה, Le-man de-amar mishum bittul piryah ve-rivyah, לחד יומא
לא משהי איניש נפשיה. le-chad yoma lo mash-hei inish nafshih. You don't
postpone for one day. What does it mean you don't postpone for
a day? So רבי גרשום Rabbi Gershom here says that it means
that since you’re not really going to be able to double up
and do it on יום טוב itself, you’re only going to be
able to sort of, you know, do it a day earlier, that’s
not going to be enough of a reason for you to postpone
getting married. I want us to before we go further take a
look quick look at this תוספות of another תוספות where he says
מפני ביטול
פריה ורביה. mipnei bittul piryah ve-rivyah. Okay. So he asks, so if
you take a
look like תוספות says like
this. The language of ביטול bittul bothers. Okay. וסעודת ברית מילה ve-seudas
bris milah מותר לעשות בחול המועד
mutar
la-asos
be-chol ha-moed דליכא שמחה de-leika simcha כדאמרינן בפרק קמא דכתובות kede-amrinan be-perek
kama de-Kesubos דלא מברכינן שהשמחה במעונו de-lo mivarchinan she-ha-simcha bi-me’ono משום דאית
ליה צערא לינוקא. mishum de-is lei tza’ara le-yanuka. Since we don’t make
a ברכה bracha שהשמחה במעונו she-ha-simcha bi-me’ono and Ashkenazim don’t make שהחיינו
she-hecheyanu because of the צער tza’ar of the תינוק, tinok, it’s not
an unqualified שמחה and therefore you can do it on חול המועד.
Okay? But he says אי נמי ei nami כיון שזמנו קבוע לבטל
זה מפני זה. keivan she-zemano kavua levatel zeh mipnei zeh. You have
to have the ברית מילה bris milah on the eighth day. So
if you have to have the ברית מילה bris milah on the
eighth day, we’re not going to tell you have the סעודה seuda
on a different day, you can’t have a different time. אבל סעודת
פדיון הבן Aval seudas pidyon ha-ben צריך עיון
אם מותר לעשות במועד. tzarich iyun im mutar la-asos be-moed. But I
don’t know about
פדיון הבן pidyon ha-ben שאין זמנו קבוע. she-ein zemano kavua. תימה בשבזמנו.
Teimah bi-she-bizmano. ונראה לי דקיימא לן דרב אשי venira li d'kayma lan
d'rav ashi etcetera. Okay, then he goes on. And let's just finish.
דדרשינן בחגיגה d'darshinan bechagiga בחגך ולא באשתך bechagecha velo be'ishtecha ואין מערבין
שמחה בשמחה. ve'ein m'arvin simcha b'simcha. So Tosafos' first answer is, you
know what? Maybe it's only a problem of getting married. Maybe there
isn't a general הלכה halacha of ואין מערבין שמחה בשמחה. ve'ein m'arvin
simcha b'simcha. It's only marriage versus wedding versus רגל. regel. It's not
a general principle, which is shocking. We normally quote the general
principle. Then he says, ועוד יש לומר ve'od yesh lomar דלא חשיב
שמחה בשמחה d'lo chashiv simcha b'simcha כי אם סעודת נישואין לבד, ki
im seudas nisuin levad, slightly different. There's a general principle, but things
like a סעודת ברית מילה seudas bris milah and a סעודת פדיון
הבן seudas pidyon haben doesn't get to the level of serious שמחה.
There might be other things that get to the level. There might
be an idea of not doing two weddings on the same day
or in the same family. It's not limited just to wedding and
רגל. regel. It's a general idea, but it has to reach a
certain threshold to be considered a real שמחה to be a problem.